So today that is דף ס"ג, Daf Samech Gimmel, במנחות, BeMenachot, and
the last דף Daf of this פרק, Perek, which was probably the
first פרק Perek that really fully directly focused on describing the types
of מנחות Menachot and how they're made and so on, which will
continue. We really have not gone like step by step the whole
process of the kneading and the baking and so on, but we're
getting very close and we're certainly seeing all of the constituent steps.
So let's take a look. We've discussed in what things get הגשה,
Hagasha, what things get תנופה. Tenufa. Now we're going to focus in
much more on the specific מנחות Menachot that are mentioned differently in
ויקרא. Vayikra. So top of the page, ס"ג עמוד א', Samech Gimmel
Amud Aleph, המשנה. HaMishna. האומר הריני עלי במחבת. Ha'omer Hareini Alai Bemachavat.
So again, the תורה Torah says that if somebody takes a מנחה,
Mincha, כי תקריב קרבן מנחה לה' סולת יהיה קרבנו ויצק עליה שמן
ונתן עליה לבונה,
Ki takriv korban mincha l'Hashem solet yihiyeh
korbano vyatzak aleha shemen v'natan aleha levona, I think I'm following the
פסוק. Pasuk. So the
פסוק Pasuk says like this, it assumes that a standard מנחה Mincha
is not baked, interestingly, flour mixed with oil. כי תקריב קרבן מנחה
לה' סולת יהיה קרבנו ויצק עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבונה. Ki takriv
korban mincha l'Hashem solet yihiyeh korbano vyatzak aleha shemen v'natan aleha levona.
Particularly hard to make sure that doesn't become חמץ. Chametz. Anyway, then
it says וכי תקריב מנחה מאפה תנור, V'chi takriv mincha ma'afeh tanur,
or if you make it one baked in an oven, ואם מנחה
על המחבת קרבנך, V'im mincha al hamachavat korbanach, if it's in like
a frying pan, ואם מנחה מרחשת קרבנך, V'im mincha marcheshet korbanach, if
it's in a deep pan, and here's how you do it. So
the standard one is unbaked, but if you specifically, the תורה Torah
described it as you happen to bring it this
way. המנחה HaMincha focuses on what type of a נדר Neder might
you have taken? You don't have to start with a נדר, Neder,
you could always just share by קרבן, Korban, but very often it
would start like a person takes a personal נדר Neder to bring
a קרבן Korban and then based on how you articulated your נדר
Neder what you have to bring. Okay, so that's the משנה's Mishna
focus. But again, the question to the afternoon is where is this
being made, at home or in the מקדש, Mikdash, not really directly
discussed here, we'll be seeing more of that later on. So let's
take a look. האומר הריני עלי במחבת. Ha'omer Hareini Alai Bemachavat. Somebody
says behold I take upon myself an obligation to bring a מנחה
Mincha in a מחבת, Machavat, which is this sort of deep pan...
I'm sorry, I keep getting this dizzy. מחבת Machavat is a simple
as a basically flat frying pan. לא יביא במרחשת, Lo yavi bemarcheshet,
don't bring in the deep pan. המרחשת, HaMarcheshet, if you say it
in a deep pan, which is the other type the תורה Torah
describes, לא יביא במחבת, Lo yavi bemachavat, don't bring in the frying
pan. What's the name of those those deeper pans? Like I have
two types of frying pans at home, one that's almost completely flat
and then another one that you can put a lid on it
that's about I don't know two inches tall. That's called the saucepan?
Okay, so that's probably more what this מרחשת Marcheshet is, is more
like a saucepan and a מחבת Machavat is more like a frying
pan.
It's also a deep fryer? Yeah, deep fryer.
Okay, but this is probably more into something like that saucepan. Okay,
so anyway, מה בין מחבת למרחשת? Ma bein machavat lemarcheshet? What is
the difference between a frying pan and a
מרחשת? Marcheshet? מרחשת יש לה כיסוי. Marcheshet yesh la kisui. Here's where
I got my description. So
the saucepan, I just never knew what it was called, the saucepan
or whatever, the מרחשת Marcheshet has a cover, ומחבת אין לה כיסוי,
U'machavat ein la kisui, and the frying pan, the מחבת, Machavat, does
not have a cover.
דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי. Divrei Rabbi Yose HaGelili. That's what רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili says. רבי חנינא בן גמליאל אומר. Rabbi Chanina
ben Gamliel Omer. רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel says,
מרחשת עמוקה. Marcheshet amuka. The מרחשת Marcheshet is deep, so that sort
of goes with the cover also. The מרחשת Marcheshet is deeper, ומעשה
רוחשין, U'ma'aseh rochashin, and when you make stuff in it, it more
like bubbles and boils and moves around. Like it's not like a
frying which is very flat, it's more like there's more liquid and
it's so... I don't know if steamy it means like the stuff
that you're cooking, you know, boiling, and not that boiling but it's
like the... if you've got flour and oil there, if I'm frying
something on a flat frying pan, right, so you know it sizzles
more than it bubbles. Right? If I've got like it's deeper, there's
more sort of you know there's more liquid going on and there's
more making matzah ball or קניידלך. Kneidlach.
Okay, that I don't know, never made either. Okay, what were you
saying?
Most people say matzah ball gives you fry, it's male and and
eggs.
Right, right, right. Okay, that's a good example, and
you fry them, but קניידלך, Kneidlach, you're boiling them in water.
Okay, but this isn't water, this is just, I mean there might
be some water in the kneading, that's you know that the גמרא
Gemara said, the משנה Mishna assumed before, the רמב"ם Rambam though limits
it, but anyway there's water in the kneading but there's not water
in the cooking.
In the cooking it's going to burn.
In the cooking it well no, but it depends how much oil
there is. You got a lot of oil, it's more like a
deep fry, if you got a lot of oil, right, so then
it's not
going to burn.
Yeah, but you
don't.
Okay, I don't know. Okay, okay, מחבת צפה, Machvat tzafa, the מחבת
Machvat however is like, you know, doesn't boil, I mean doesn't bubble,
it more like a צפה tzafa literally means like it floats on
top, meaning it's like, you know, the stuff is it's not immersed
in oil, it's flat, it's obviously frying in oil, but it's not
immersed, and ומעשה קשין, u'ma'aseh kashin, and what you make of it
is harder, right, it's not like it's soft and liquidy when you
fry stuff, it's, you know, it's hard, it's solid. Okay. So basically
one is more of a frying pan and the other's more of
a sauce pan. So let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara,
מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי, mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Yosi, what's the reasoning of
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that says that's the difference about having a
cover or not having a
cover? אילימא מרחשת דאתיא ארחושי הלב. eileima Marcheshet de'asya a'chushi ha'leiv.
Now I think Rifka you asked me this question before, since you're
not making it, it's being made in the מקדש, Mikdash, and you're
just bringing the ingredients and ingredients are the same, why would you
designate to make one that one type of a thing over another?
Now first of all it's not so clear you're not making it,
I mean that we're going to see as I said before, if
you assume that once the oil you use to המתינה פלח hamitah
falach you can't take it out of the מקדש, Mikdash, then you're
right, it's probably being made by the כהנים, Kohanim, but for now
we'll assume it's being made in the מקדש Mikdash by the כהנים,
Kohanim, but I'm going to leave that as still an open question,
there is a possibility. But let's say you're right. So why would
you be motivated to bring one over the other if you're not
even making it yourself? So the גמרא's Gemara going to say, and
it's really fascinating because, you know, it just shows how removed we
are from this world, is that they might have different symbolisms that
have been lost to us, right? So one type of a thing
made one way might be symbolic of one thing and made a
different way might be symbolic of another. And the גמרא's Gemara really
going to try to reconstruct that and it's going to say maybe
the word מרחשת, Marcheshet, which is like, you know, the movement and
the boiling and also it's going to say that the word רחוש
rachush means, as we'll see, sort of like, you know, thoughts, thoughts
of the heart. So therefore maybe that has to do with more
you're bringing it because of because you, you know, you had bad
thoughts that you want to atone for, something going on with sort
of your inner thoughts. So that's the concept of
מרחשת. Marcheshet. מרחשת דאתיא ארחושי הלב, Marcheshet de'asya a'chushi ha'leiv, the sort
of thoughts or the movements of the heart.
Right. רש"י Rashi says הרהור עבירה. hirhur aveira. דכתיב רחש לבי דבר
טוב, de'ksiv rachash libi davar tov, now there it's the positive, my
heart sort of, you know,
emoted, felt a good thing. So רחוש rachush is connected with the
heart and therefore to a heart is covered, right, your heart is
inside your body, so therefore it would be a cover type of
a thing. So that's like an interesting symbolism, a covered כלי, kli,
the thing is moving like, you know, the movements of your heart,
the thought of your heart, that's a מרחשת. Marcheshet. ומחבת, u'Machvat, what's
the idea of a מחבת, Machvat, a frying pan? דאתיא אמחבואי הפה.
de'asya a'machbu'ei ha'peh. The word מחבת, Machvat, מחבואי machbu'ei can be connected
to the idea of speaking, utterances. Where do you see that? כדאמרי
אינשי, k'd'amri inshi, like people say, מנבח ניבוחי, minvach nivuchei, like he
sort of uttered or spoke, literally actually it means barked, but it
could be used by people, not just by dogs. So the word
מחבת Machvat could be associated with the idea of speech, and speech
is uncovered, you're actually saying things. So here, by the way, it's
also interesting to compare it to an עולה. Olah. You know, we
said a couple of times a מנחה Mincha is a type of
a poor person's עולה, Olah, and an עולה Olah the גמרא Gemara
very much associates with הרהורי הלב, hirhurei ha'leiv, with having like thoughts
of עבירה. aveira. So here it's associating the same thing with the
מנחה, Mincha, just going the thought one step further. Speaking bad things,
okay, it's still one step prior to action, although speaking could actually
be an עבירה aveira itself, not just the planning for an עבירה.
aveira. רש"י Rashi talks about רכילות ולשון הרע rechilut v'lashon hara and
slander, which goes often to be much more destructive than an actual,
you know, physical action. But anyway, it's interesting trying to associate why
would a person bring a מנחה Mincha and saying therefore the symbolism,
you know, covered versus opened up and how the word sounds like
other types of words, what the symbolism might be. So that might
be what's indicated for רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi difference between covered and
uncovered the vessel. So the גמרא Gemara says, "Wait a minute. אימא
איפכא. eima ipcha. How do you know that's the symbolism? Maybe the
symbolism is the opposite.
מחבת דאתיא אמחבואי הלב, Machvat de'asya a'machbu'ei ha'leiv, מחבת Machvat maybe is
for the hidden thoughts of the heart. מחבת Machvat like
מחבוא machvo could be like a, you know, sort of like in
hiding. So the hidden thoughts of the heart. דכתיב למה נחבאת לבורח,
de'ksiv lama nachbeisa livroach, לבן Lavan said to יעקב, Yaakov, 'Why did
you deceive or hide from me, you know, your intention to run
away?' So מחבת Machvat could mean the hidden thoughts of the heart,
and therefore making it מחבת Machvat should be covered, not מרחשת. Marcheshet.
And that's the one coming for the heart.
ומרחשת דאתיא ארחושי, u'Marcheshet de'asya a'rachushi, so it's the movements of the
lips. לרחש lirchash can literally mean to move. So rather than the
movement of the heart, the moving of the lips, that would be
coming on speech. כדאמרי אינשי, k'd'amri inshi, like people say,
הוה מרחשן שפוותיה, hava merachshan sifvosei, his lips were moving or, you
know, were muttering or something. So therefore you see you could, the
symbolism might be the exact opposite. Which is coming for thoughts, which
is coming for speech? Therefore which should be covered, which should be
uncovered?" So my point is אלא גמרא גמירי לה, ella Gemara gemiri
lah, you're right. He didn't just look at the פסוק pasuk and
figure it out based on what the words mean, obviously the symbolism
is X, because maybe the symbolism was Y. He has a tradition
that a מחבת machavat is flat and a... is uncovered and a
מרחשת marcheshet is covered. Now again, it's not necessarily that he and
רבי חנניה בן גמליאל Rabbi Chananya ben Gamliel are arguing, right, one
speaks about deep and flat, the other cover and uncover, they both
of those characteristics could be true. But what I find interesting about
this גמרא Gemara is that, you know, it's really trying to answer
in a way Rivka's question, who cares how what you're bringing, it's
all the same ingredients? Well, we don't know. It just shows you
how distant we are from that world, you know, that we don't
have any symbolic associations with these things where they might have. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes on. רבי חנניה בן גמליאל Rabbi
Chananya ben Gamliel אומר, omer, so he spoke about flat versus deep,
מרחשת marcheshet עמוקה, amuka, how do you know a מרחשת marcheshet is
deep? דכתיב, de-ketiv, now this maybe is more in the פסוק, pasuk,
it says וכל נעשה במרחשת, ve-chol na'aseh ba-marcheshet, in the מרחשת, marcheshet,
which implies that there's an in, that there's a real like, you
know, inner space, so therefore it really has some
depth. ולבתר ve-le-vatar שפה sapah מחבת machavat צפה, tzafah, הרינו, hareinu, so
a מחבת machavat sort of floats on the top is flat. דכתיב
de-ketiv ועל מחבת, ve-al machavat, on the מחבת, machavat, not in, right,
you're saying that you're frying something, well what do we say, we
can say in a frying pan, we don't say on a frying
pan. We say we're grilling on the grill, but we say we're
frying in a frying pan.
But okay, but what do you say in a skillet?
On the skillet.
On the skillet is a...
why would we say on a... because a skillet is totally flat,
has no walls. Right. That's sort of like grilling on a grill.
So anyway, that is a very close פירוש perush to the פסוק,
pasuk, on versus in. So one actually is deep and the other
is relatively flat. Okay, so that makes sense. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan,
בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim, now בית שמאי Beit Shammai says,
האומר הרי עלי מרחשת, ha-omer harei alai marcheshet, I take upon myself
a מרחשת. marcheshet. Now what type of a vow did he make?
יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו, yehei munach ad she-yavo Eliyahu, it should
be set aside until אליהו Eliyahu comes. And that's funny, you talk
about setting aside an object until אליהו Eliyahu comes, that's an interesting
way the גמרא Gemara articulate, you know, it's so funny when we
sort of refer to like, you know, the fact, I mean normally
it's a legal system, so bringing in אליהו הנביא. Eliyahu HaNavi. Also
it's interesting why they tend to focus on אליהו, Eliyahu, you know,
because not that he's going to פסקן pasken for us, but presumably
the assumption is that אליהו Eliyahu will clarify the facts, not not
clarify הלכה. halacha. So often the גמרא Gemara uses that if you
have no way of reconciling it, what do you do? So it's
sort of like you put it in permanent escrow, you put it
permanently aside, there's no way to determine. So sometimes it does this
by a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot debate, basically two people entrusted money
to me, one person two hundred dollars, one person one hundred, and
I forgot who's who. And of course they come and each one
says that they gave me the two hundred dollars. So what do
you do? So well you give each one back a hundred, because
they each obviously deserve a hundred, and says the third hundred יהא
מונח עד שיבוא אליהו. yehei munach ad she-yavo Eliyahu. You just basically
put it in permanent escrow, there's nothing to be done about it.
I can't give it to either one of them because maybe I'm
stealing the other one. So here too בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
we don't know what you mean, so leave it to אליהו Eliyahu
comes. But wait, I only took a vow. So רש״י Rashi says
leave the issue undetermined, you don't know what you have to bring,
you're not going to bring it until אליהו Eliyahu comes. תוספות Tosafot
says that no, maybe we actually relate it to an object. I
took some of the money or some flour and I said this
should be for a מחבת. machavat. So what does that mean? Leave
it till אליהו Eliyahu comes. Now why do I not know what
it means? Doesn't it mean a מנחת מחבת? minchat machavat? No, because
I didn't say I'm going to bring a מנחת מחבת. minchat machavat.
I said הרי עלי, harei alai, what's the phrase it uses here?
הרי עלי מרחשת. harei alai marcheshet. Behold on me is a מרחשת.
marcheshet. Now what does that mean? So let's take a look at
what it could mean. יהא מונח עד שיבוא אליהו, yehei munach ad
she-yavo Eliyahu, מספקא להו, mesapka lehu, they're uncertain, אי על שום כלי
נקראו או על שום מעשיהם. ei al shum kli nikre-u o al
shum ma'aseihem. What does מרחשת marcheshet mean? Is מרחשת marcheshet the name
of the vessel? This is a מרחשת marcheshet is a saucepan, let's
say. Or does it mean מרחשת marcheshet is an adjective or it's
to it describes the type of a מנחה mincha and it means
like a bubbling מנחה. mincha. So how would it matter? Because if
the word מרחשת marcheshet means saucepan and I said הרי עלי מרחשת,
harei alai marcheshet, I'm vowing to give a saucepan to the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. I'm not vowing to give a קרבן, korban, right?
The קרבן korban is not called a מרחשת, marcheshet, the קרבן korban
is מנחה על המרחשת mincha al ha-marcheshet or no not על המרחשת,
al ha-marcheshet, במרחשת קרבנך. be-marcheshet korbanecha. So if I said מנחת מרחשת,
minchat marcheshet, I could use it as a descriptor. But the word
מרחשת marcheshet by itself just means a sauce pan. So that is
if מרחשת marcheshet means the כלי. kli. מרחשת marcheshet is more of
an adjective, it's describing a type of a מנחה, mincha, it's not
the name of the כלי, kli, or you know saying a bubbling,
so if I said behold on me is a bubbling, so it
obviously talking about a כלי, kli, so it must mean a bubbling
מנחה mincha and it's describing a מנחה. mincha. So I don't know
what to do with the, let's say תוספות's Tosafot scenario, with the
money I sanctified, does it go towards one or does it go
towards the other? So therefore I leave the money עד שיבוא אליהו.
ad she-yavo Eliyahu.
If it's the money to I mean, wouldn't you know
what, right, I could put... well, and that's תוספות's Tosafot question, don't
you know what you meant? And how much by נדר neder do
we go by what you meant, how much do we go by,
you know, what it objectively means? If you look at the last
line of this תוספות... Tosafot...
Tosafos has a different question than Rifka's. Look at the תוספות מסתפקא
להו Tosafos mistapka lehu about seven lines before it ends where it
says ויש לומר. v'yeish lomar. It starts with the word אלמא מנדר.
alma mineder. Okay?
So he says ויש לומר דמיירי כגון דאמר מעות הללו, v'yeish lomar
d'mairi k'gon d'amar maos halalu, this money, okay, which makes it so
it's more ambiguous whether you're planning on giving a מנחה mincha or
not if you're talking about money. או סולת זה, o soles zeh,
or this flour, למרחשת. l'marcheshes. And you don't know whether you mean,
you know, it's not clear whether that means for the כלי, kli,
to be used for the כלי kli or to be used for
the קרבן. korban. But then he says מיהו קשיא, mihu kashya, but
it's still difficult, that טאקע מעות הללו, takke maos halalu, there's a
way to fix this whole thing. Now not Rifka's which is go
by what you think, but he says here's how you can fix
it. יביא מעות דחולין, yavi maos d'chullin, get other money, ויקנה מרחשת,
v'yikneh marcheshes, go buy with that the frying pan, ויאמר דאם כלי
נדר, v'yomar d'im kli nadar, if I made a vessel, if I
meant a vessel, יהא כלי קנוי בהן, ye'ei kli kanu ba-hen, then
the קדושה kedusha should transfer to this vessel I bought with the
other money. And if I didn't mean a vessel, then then this
כלי kli I'm giving to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and this
money I'm going to use to buy, you know, a to bring
a מנחה. mincha. Meaning, why do we let the money stay? Normally
we try to fix this situation. We say you're stuck, bring both
and transfer the money, you know, appropriately, whichever one I meant קדושה'ס
kedusha's transferred and here's the other one and I brought both. Why
don't we say that? So it's not exactly your question but תוספות
Tosafos says isn't there a way out of it? So תוספות Tosafos
says he creates a crazy scenario. What?
Additional monetary law.
I know, but תוספות Tosafos points out normally we'd make that demand
of you if you got yourself into this bind. Okay, rather than
having all this money sitting around and possibly being misused and you
never fulfilling your vow, we say, okay, you put yourself in this
bind, you know, now cover your bases. Okay, so that's a normal
approach. So תוספות Tosafos says why don't we say that? So תוספות'ס
Tosafos's answer is ויש לומר דכגון שהפריש מעות והקדישן למרחשת, v'yeish lomar
d'chegon she'hifrish maos v'hikdishan l'marcheshes, למה שידרשו חכמי הלשון, l'mah she'yidreshu chachmei
ha-lashon, חכמת הלשון, chochmat ha-lashon, which he says
this money should be למרחשת, l'marcheshes, I don't even know what I
mean, but however the rabbis decide to interpret or the linguists, תוספות
Tosafos says he doesn't even say the rabbis, it's the linguists decide
to interpret what this what I just said, that's how the money
should be used. So therefore it's not like I meant one but
we don't know which one, but like we could sort of say
cover your bases, like you either meant one or the you know
or the other, you know, but it's all dependent on how we
are going to legally determine what it means. Anyway, besides תוספות'ס Tosafos's
sort of funny question, whatever funny question, you know, way of framing
it, not the question's funny, but the framing is funny. It does
point to the interesting question that Rifka asks, you know, which is,
how much do we interpret what you said based on sort of
form, you know, sort of our determination of what the language means
and how much do we determine what you said based on your
clarifying what you meant? And that's always a question by נדרים, nedarim,
you know, on the one hand you go אחר לשון בני אדם
achar lashon bnei adam as opposed to לשון המקרא, lashon ha-mikra, you
go by the vernacular not by some you know what like biblical
usage. On the other hand, how much does it go by you
know we normally say פיו ולבו שוין, piv v'libo shavin,
until your heart and what you say is equal, but so therefore
what you're thinking has a strong impact. And normally, our normal principle
is דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim she'ba-lev einan devarim, that what you're
thinking doesn't matter in all sort of legal things, it's what you
actually say, what's external, what's accessible to all. But that is mostly
true when you're dealing with things that are two-party transactions, particularly like
a מקח וממכר, mekach u'memkar, commerce, there you could say or contracts,
I don't care what you were thinking, I care what you said,
that's what's accessible to everybody and that's how we're going to judge
the nature of what was done. When you're talking more about things
that what?
You see that in secular law. Right, the interpretation of a contract
unless the party that did it wrote it up.
Okay, that's interesting. But here so here it's not left to either
side, it's left to a third party so to say, what did
it objectively mean? But when you're dealing with one-sided transactions and particularly
you could have one-sided transactions
in commerce like a gift, right, דאותו, d'oto, how much of the
gift you try to speculate on the intention of the giver because
it was one-sided? And particularly one-sided more of ritual nature like a
קרבן korban and a נדר, neder, there you could imagine that you
would use much more the what we're going to speculate that you
meant. And if you tell us you meant something, how much would
that inform? So Rifka's question, which is why don't we say, you
know, that why don't we just ask you what you said is
a very good question. תוספות Tosafos thinks of a very funny scenario
like you said I'm going to say it means whatever people say
it means, but I would also add to this that there's another
position of בית שמאי Beis Shammai when it comes to הקדש, hekdesh,
which is a debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, we're going to about to see בית הלל Beis Hillel
in a minute, that בית שמאי Beis Shammai says הקדש בטעות hekdesh
b'ta'us is still הקדש. hekdesh. And בית הלל Beis Hillel says הקדש
בטעות hekdesh b'ta'us is not הקדש. hekdesh. So what we see is
that in general when it comes to הקדש, hekdesh, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai is less concerned about what you're thinking and he's much more
focuses on the speech as a speech act and you said it
and it has objective meaning and I don't care if you didn't
mean to say it. Whereas בית הלל Beis Hillel says הקדש בטעות
hekdesh b'ta'us is not הקדש, hekdesh, is concerned more with how much
what did you really mean. Okay, so anyway that part makes it
an excellent question but presumably that is בית שמאי'ס Beis Shammai's position.
We don't care so much about what you're thinking, we go what
you said, it's indeterminate what you said, why don't you try to
fix it, that's תוספות'ס Tosafos's question, but anyway you leave it עד
שיבוא אליהו. ad sheyavo Eliyahu. Yes, Mordechai?
Could we have framed the whole thing differently as to the question
of what it is as a question post מקדש. Mikdash. So when
we're saying leave it, we're not posing our normal solutions because there
is no normal solution, there's no מקדש Mikdash anyway. You've made this
נדר, neder, we're just going to leave it, because there's no point
in trying to make a restitution, there's nothing to give it to.
Because we had the הוה אמינא hava amina that in the מקדש
Mikdash there was a מסורת massoret of what these two things were,
that was very clear for people, the symbolism that existed then, so
there wouldn't be the question that we have now in terms of
well, which one is it?
Well, okay, I hear your point. Hold on, I have to, Jeb
was saying that there was some problem with the microphone, it's better.
I hear your point. The point is that בית שמאי Beis Shammai
and בית הלל Beis Hillel are talking in the time of the
מקדש. Mikdash. So, you know, שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel lived in
the time of the מקדש, Mikdash, and I don't think that they,
even if the בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel
went beyond the period of the מקדש, Mikdash, but I don't think
that, you know, unless they're explicitly saying בזמן הזה, bazman hazeh, even
if the person speaking about it is בזמן הזה, bazman hazeh, when
we're talking about מקדש-related Mikdash things, they're imagining what the הלכה halacha
would be at that time. So, I don't think
that that would be appropriate to read in, both given the dating
of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel and also
just in general, we don't assume that unless I think, because you
know they're sort of imagining virtually as if this was still around.
So sometimes they do talk, you know, somebody says בזמן הזה bazman
hazeh הרי עלי harei alai whatever, how do you handle the situation?
But usually you need those words בזמן הזה. bazman hazeh.
Okay, Aryeh, did you have a question? No? Okay, fine. All right,
so let's take a look. So that's בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says we don't know what you mean and יהא
מונח. yehei munach. ובית הלל אומרים, u'Veis Hillel omrim, and בית הלל
Beis Hillel says, כלי היה במקדש ומרחשת שמה. kli hayah ba'Mikdash u'marcheshes
shemah.
No, it's very clear that a מרחשת marcheshes is a כלי kli
and therefore implicitly if you say הרי עלי מרחשת, harei alai marcheshes,
you're actually donating a vessel to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, not
a מנחה. mincha. So as opposed to what I was trying to
say that בית הלל Beis Hillel would, you know, more focus on
what you were thinking and want to know what you were thinking,
here he doesn't have to go there because here he actually thinks
that it's very clear what the language, what the words meant. מרחשת
marcheshes is a vessel, so you actually were donating a vessel, if
that's what you said. Now he's going to describe this vessel. ודומה
כמין קלבוס עמוק. v'domeh k'min kalvos amuk. It's like a deep קלבוס,
kalvos, which was a certain type of a vessel. Now
רש"י Rashi says, you know, that it was, there are two pictures
in רש"י. Rashi. If you look at the column here in the
שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes on the left-hand side, you know, it sort
of shows like I think, what is
that, like a double boiler or a deep fryer, something that has
walls in the middle of the vessel itself. For what? For muffins?
To make for like muffins.
Well, that's the picture in the רש"י Rashi itself, it looks like
a muffin pan. Right. In this picture, it looks like there's more
one central space. But anyway, there are like indented spaces within it,
so it's deep and there are indented spaces within it. Okay, that's
what this מרחשת marcheshes was. וכשבצק נחת בתוכו, u'keshebatzeik nach b'tocho,
when the dough is in it, meaning presumably in the indent, דומה
כמין תפוחי הברטין. domeh k'min tapuchei habartin.
It's like the... רש"י Rashi says this sort of means like the
warts that grow on trees. You know, when a big wart or
whatever growth grows on trees, it like protrudes out. So here too,
you know, these things would be like sort of protruding out, these
dough pieces, you know, sort of like it would be protruding. I
mean, I guess if you think of it like a muffin pan,
right, so you have all the sort of things, the dough things
that are protruding, you know, out, depending on which side you're looking
at it from, out of the vessel. Okay. וכמין בלוטי היוונין, u'k'min
blutei hayevanim, and like whatever the בלוטי, blutei, some type of
Greek...
He says acorn.
Acorns. Greek acorns.
Of the Greek oak.
Okay, very good. ואומר, v'omer, okay, therefore, that's what it was. ואומר
כל הנעשה במרחשת ובמחבת. v'omer kol hana'aseh b'marcheshes u'va'machavas. And it says
anything done in a מרחשת marcheshes and on a מחבת, machavas, so
you see 'in' means that it had these sort of protrusions and
it was inside a deeper כלי. kli. אלמא על שם הכלים נקראו
ולא על שם המעשים. alma al shem hakeilim nikre'u v'lo al shem
hama'asim. So you see according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai versus בית
הלל, Beis Hillel, these words refer to the actual vessels, not as
just adjectives, and therefore if somebody says הרי עלי מרחשת, harei alai
marcheshes, they're donating a vessel. And they're not, they don't mean a
מנחת מרחשת. minchas marcheshes. So there you have those two types of
vessels. Now we go from the מרחשת marcheshes and the מחבת machavas
to the מאפה תנור. ma'afeh tanur. Let's take a look. הרי עלי
בתנור, harei alai b'tanur, somebody says I'm going to bring
the מנחה mincha that comes in a תנור. tanur. Notice if you
said הרי עלי, harei alai, the בית beis is key, because בית
שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel debate if you say
הרי עלי מרחשת, harei alai marcheshes, that might mean you're giving the
vessel. ב, b', in a מרחשת, marcheshes, clearly means the מנחה mincha
that is brought in the מרחשת. marcheshes. So the בית beis is
key. הרי עלי בתנור, harei alai b'tanur, the stuff that comes in
a תנור, tanur, לא יביא מעשה קופח. lo yavi ma'aseh kupach. Don't
bring something that is made in a קופח. kupach. A קופח kupach
is a small individual oven. They had like small ovens, basically the
ovens that they had were like teepees almost, you know, where they
had a fire at the bottom, I left, I forgot to bring,
I have a book that has pictures of this. Anyway, they had
a fire at the bottom, you have like a teepee, you know,
the pot went on the inside on the top, on the inside,
so the heat rose and got, you know, concentrated at the top
and that, that's how it cooked. So that would, and that was
a small one for an individual. A
larger one was a what do you call it, a כירה kira
which was basically you know for for more than one pot. So
let's take a look. So if you say do not bring a
מעשה כופח ma'aseh kupach ולא מעשה רעפים v'lo ma'aseh re'afim and not
something that is basically baked on
what are those called on a flat surface on tiles? Thank you,
that's what I was looking for. Not baked on tiles.
ומעשה יורות uma'aseh yorot or not something ומעשה יורות הערביים uma'aseh yorot
ha'arviyim not something baked in Arab
pots. So sometimes they would actually use a type of a pot
as where they would as where the baking would take place. Not
inside of an oven but in a pot itself. So that is
not a baking of an oven. It has to actually be an
oven. Now by the way, the fact that it's describing this and
notice now it's not
saying get all of these משניות mishnayot suggest that you are doing
the baking yourself. If you look at the previous משנה mishna it
was לא יביא במחבת lo yavi bemachvat right לא יביא במרחשת. lo
yavi bemarcheshet. Don't bring it in a מחבת. machvat. Don't bring it
in a מרחשת. marcheshet. Here it's saying לא יביא lo yavi don't
bring something that you baked in this type of a vessel or
that type of a vessel. So the suggestion is you're baking it
at home or frying at home and then you're bringing it.
Okay, so so הערביים ha'arviyim the
Arabs.
But what are they meaning? Who did they refer to?
I mean
Arabia existed prior to Islam. Not about I mean Arab is a
identifier right it goes back to to the time of the משנה
mishna already. Right? They I mean Arabia was there.
There were Greeks around them.
Yeah, but I mean they lived in Rome which obviously you know
I mean I don't know. You do have references to ערביים. arviyim.
I always I never looked into it but I'm
wondering who would they have called ערביים.
arviyim. I mean the גמרא gemara often talks to about a טייעא
tayya like about sort of like a nomads and refers to Arabs
as nomads. I don't know. I'd have to look into that. Okay,
so anyway, but the point is don't bring it. So here's the
vessels you do and don't make it in. But the other point
I'm pointing out which I think is interesting is you're assumed to
be making it at home and bringing it. Okay, and that's something
that we're going to have to continue to look at, but you
are making this suggests that very strongly.
Okay, where were we? רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer Rabbi Yehuda
says רוצה מביא מעשה כופח. rotza mevi ma'aseh kupach.
You can bring a מעשה כופח ma'aseh kupach that is a type
of an oven. It's a smaller oven but it is a type
of an oven. הרי עלי מנחת מאפה harei alay minchat ma'afeh now
if you say you're going to bring this מנחה mincha this baked
מנחה mincha לא יביא מחצה חלות ומחצה רקיקין. lo yavi mechetza challot
umechetza rekikin. Remember the Torah says סולת חלות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי מצות
משוחים
בשמן. solet challot belulot bashamen urkikey matzot meshuchim bashamen. You shall bring
you know breads made with oil and wafers made with oil. So
the גמרא gemara understands or the whatever the first opinion in the
משנה mishna understands it's one or the other. Either bring bread, loaves,
or wafers but do not bring some breads and some wafers. It
has to be one or the other. רבי שמעון מתיר Rabbi Shimon
matir Rabbi Shimon allows you to bring some of each מפני שהוא
קרבן אחד mipnei shehu korban echad because it's all one קרבן korban
of two variations but you can bring of a mix. Okay, תנו
רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So first we're going to look at the vessels
then we're going to look about doing the half and half. מאפה
תנור ולא מעשה כופח. ma'afeh tanur v'lo ma'aseh kupach.
So it has to be מאפה תנור ma'afeh tanur a real oven
and not this כופח. kupach. ולא מעשה רעפים v'lo ma'aseh re'afim
and not on tiles. ולא מעשה יורות הערביים v'lo ma'aseh yorot ha'arviyim
and not on these Arab pots which apparently you could cook it
in. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer תנור תנור tanur tanur שני
פעמים shnei pe'amim להכשיר מעשה כופח. lehachshir ma'aseh kupach. It says תנור
tanur twice in the פסוק pasuk so telling you you know instead
of like אין ריבוי אחר ריבוי אלא לרבות. ein ribuy achar ribuy
ella lerabot. So since it says תנור tanur twice it means it
doesn't have to be exactly a תנור tanur and it can even
be a כופח kupach this lesser תנור. tanur. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi
Shimon omer תנור תנור tanur tanur שני פעמים. shnei pe'amim. No, Rabbi
Shimon says it's not coming to include a כופח. kupach. What's it
coming to include? So אחד שתהא אפייתם בתנור echad shetehei afiyatam batanur
ואחד שתהא הקדשם בתנור. v'echad shetehei hekdesham batanur.
Now this is going to get interesting because this turns a little
bit to the question about where's it being done. So it says
תנור tanur twice to tell you two things. Number one baked in
a תנור tanur but number two it's becomes sanctified in the תנור.
tanur. The תנור tanur was there was a תנור tanur in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash which was a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So
if you're baking in the תנור tanur in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash that is where it's being put in the כלי שרת kli
sharet to become sanctified.
Now question is why didn't it become sanctified earlier? Because it uses
oil and the oil we saw was מידת לח middat lach and
that was used a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So that's a little
bit unclear why he's why that's not the case. But he's saying
that the oven is what's what sanctified it. The גמרא gemara actually
will question this. Let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara. אטו
ומי אית ליה
לרבי שמעון האי סברא? atu umi it lei l'Rabbi Shimon hai sevara?
Does Rabbi Shimon really hold it that it's the תנור tanur that
sanctifies it? והתנן vehatnan we taught in the משנה mishna which we'll
see later on רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer לעולם הוי רגיל
לומר le'olam hevei ragil lomar you should accustom yourself to say if
you're trying to remember all the הלכות halachot of מנחה mincha the
following שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים כשרות בעזרה sh'tei halechem v'lechem hapanim kesherot
ba'azarah the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem and the לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim
are כשרות kesherot in the עזרה, azarah, obviously, וכשרות בבית פאגי, u-kesherot
be-Veit Pagi,
they're also כשרות kesherot even to bring outside the עזרה azarah in
בית פאגי, Veit Pagi, בית פאגי, Veit Pagi, it's a local, we'll
see what it means where רש"י Rashi says it's somewhat of the
space right outside of the wall of the עזרה. azarah. So therefore,
why is that a question? So here's what the גמרא's Gemorah doing,
the question is, it says, this is the simple way to understand
the question is like this: if they were already sanctified, if you're
talking about the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem and the לחם הפנים, lechem
ha-panim, presumably you don't mean when they're dough, you mean after they're
baked. Now if you're after they're baked and you take them out
of the מקדש, Mikdash, so if they were already sanctified in the
תנור, tannur, wouldn't that become פסול ביוצא? pasul be-yotzei? And therefore you've
got a problem, how does it not become פסול ביוצא? pasul be-yotzei?
Now תוספות Tosafot actually says an earlier תוספות Tosafot is a whole
discussion based on another גמרא, Gemorah, which is a fascinating idea, which
is, well let me sort of tell you what the challenge of
all of this is. It is quite fascinating that I keep on
pointing out that a מנחה minchah as opposed to an animal קרבן,
korban, the full קדושה kedushah does not come right away from the
moment you sanctify. I have my cow and I say this is
an עולה, olah, that already gives it קדושת הגוף, kedushat ha-guf, I'll
transgress מעילה, me'ilah, I don't need any כלי שרת. klei sharet. Now
it's true I can take it out of the בית המקדש Beit
Ha-Mikdash before it gets שחט, shechted, okay, but it already starts pretty
much with קדושת הגוף. kedushat ha-guf. By a מנחה, minchah, that's where
I say הרי זו למנחה, harei zu le-minchah, that's more קדושת דמים
kedushat damim and it needs a כלי שרת kli sharet and it
needs all these stages to give it full קדושה. kedushah. Now and
that's where we're talking about the oven etc. Now one of the
things the גמרא Gemorah does say is that when I'm dealing with
a מנחה minchah that comes with an animal like שתי הלחם shtei
ha-lechem is a good example, that it does not get full קדושת
הגוף kedushat ha-guf until I do זריקת הדם zerikat ha-dam of the
animals, which means that if I take it out of the בית
המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash it's not פסול. pasul. This leads תוספות Tosafot to
a question which is, is this true about all מנחות menachot or
just something that comes with an animal? If it comes with an
animal, it doesn't get full קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf until the blood
is thrown. Maybe if it's not with an animal it gets full
קדושת הגוף kedushat ha-guf even earlier. So the question he says is,
is it possible to take a מנחה minchah outside of the בית
המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash after its קדושת כלי? kedushat kli?
And he thinks it's possible. Now and again intuitively you would say
the animal case is different and once it has קדושת כלי, kedushat
kli, כלי שרת, kli sharet, you can't take it out of the
מקדש. Mikdash. That's the whole idea because it has קדושת הגוף. kedushat
ha-guf. But תוספות Tosafot thinks it's possible that no, מנחה minchah is
different and even after קדושת כלי kedushat kli you can take it
out of the בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. There's no פסול יוצא. psul
yotzei. So then what's the גמרא's Gemorah question? Here the גמרא's Gemorah
question is more like it's not appropriate. If it really had קדושת
כלי kedushat kli you wouldn't be taking it out, not like it
would פסול pasul it to take it out but you wouldn't be
like לכתחילה lechatchilah untroubled by the fact that it was taken out.
So that's the question. Again that's not פשט. pshat. פשט Pshat is
is that once it has קדושת כלי kedushat kli it really is
פסול ביוצא. pasul be-yotzei. But again I point out this תוספות, Tosafot,
a fascinating idea that how different a מנחה minchah is from an
animal קרבן korban and the roles of being sanctifying it until it
gets its full sanctity. Okay, so that being said let's focus back
on the גמרא's Gemorah question. The גמרא's Gemorah question is, how can
you say the oven sanctified it if it was already sanctified, why
can you take it out of the בית המקדש? Beit Ha-Mikdash? Either
it's פסול ביוצא pasul be-yotzei or it's inappropriate. More simply it's פסול
ביוצא. pasul be-yotzei. If it's sanctified, how could you be taking it
out of the בית המקדש? Beit Ha-Mikdash? So let's see what the
גמרא's Gemorah answer is. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אימא, eima, you're right,
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it is not that the oven
sanctified it yet, but אימא שיהא הקדשן לשום תנור. eima she-yehei hekdeshan
leshum tannur.
When you're sanctifying it you should say not only I'm sanctifying this
as to be used for the מנחה, minchah, but you should actually
say I'm sanctifying this that it should be used for the מנחה
minchah of מאפה תנור, ma'afeh tannur, to be sanctified, so therefore you
specifically have in mind the specific type of מנחה minchah that you
want to use it for. Now that's a radical reread, it starts
by saying that it has to be sanctified in the תנור, tannur,
now he's just telling you a הלכה halachah that you have to
have in mind the type of מנחה. minchah. But again I want
to take a step back, bracketing how much of a reread that
was, I want to just take a step back and appreciate this
question about the קדושה kedushah of the מנחה. minchah. So here we're
saying that even after you've baked it, it might not have even
presumably if you baked it in the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash where
we were thinking you were baking it in a כלי שרת kli
sharet etc. But anyway even after you've baked it is still not
fully sanctified, you could take it out of the בית המקדש. Beit
Ha-Mikdash. Which also means that you can be baking it and making
it and starting outside of the בית המקדש, Beit Ha-Mikdash, right? Because
here we're saying that that sanctity doesn't occur yet at that time
of the making and the baking etc. So according to that again
points to the fact that this could all be made outside the
בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. You bake it, you fry it, what's suggested
in משנה, Mishnah, then you bring it and then the problem, the
need to keep it in the בית המקדש, Beit Ha-Mikdash, that level
of sanctity would only occur later. Okay, so that yes, so that
is where the גמרא Gemorah reread רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to even
after the baking to allow this to be outside the בית המקדש.
Beit Ha-Mikdash.
Yes, but even if you designate does a כהן kohen have to
be present?
How
could you have this associated if in the מקדש Mikdash there'd even
have to be some... Yeah, you'd have to trust people to do
it correctly and
especially if the question
is like... Right, I mean you know, you'd certainly, you know, right,
you could imagine nowadays, oh you have to come with your תעודה
teudah and your הכשר, hechsher, right? Even the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
right?
Which is what is really, it really,
it really makes this fascinating.
On the one hand, by animals the שחיטה shechitah can be done
by a זר, zar, but the animal have to be standing in
the עזרה azarah and the כהנים Kohanim are observing it. Right, and
here, if you're like bringing from your home and you're the one
that constructed the whole thing, that's like surprising that we would sort
of allow that to be done without sort of direct supervision. So
you're right, there's on the one hand the קדושה kedushah question, when
is it sanctified that it must keep in the מקדש, Mikdash, but
there's also this whole issue about sort of letting go of a
certain amount of control.
Exactly, that's the keyword, trust. Letting go of control in, you know,
in the bringing of these מנחות. minchos. So we actually see, by
the way I should say in a somewhat analogous way, that by
the animals the fact that they require checking for מום mum four
days beforehand, question was it תמיד Tamid or was it every animal?
Anyway, it didn't have to be done in the מקדש. Mikdash. The
גמרא Gemara spoke about buying it
from people who whatever middlemen, traders, sellers, who actually they did their
checking. And there you could also certainly understand that there's a financial
incentive, you know, to lie or to not fully do your job
or whatever. So there is an interesting issue here about, you know,
trust and not fully supervising everything.
There is the אופסידא דמתא, ofseida d'masa, you have the reputation defense
as a person.
Right, and also a מום mum presumably could be seen.
You start getting מומים mumim through your animals, a מום mum that's
rejected, you go back to the guy and... that's a good point
too. That is a good point.
What could go wrong kid? It's flour.
First of all, maybe you used the wrong vessel. Well, first I
baked it, then I fried it, or whatever, or you didn't have
the right ingredients. You didn't have a full סולת soles or whatever,
you didn't have a full לוג. log. Right. Okay. הרי עלי מנחת
מאפה לא יביא מחצה, Harei alai minchas ma'afeh lo yavi mechtzah,
so now it's מאפה תנור. ma'afeh tanur. Don't bring half and half
of the loaves and the wafers. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, וכי תקריב,
V'chi sakriv, when you bring, this is the פסוק pasuk about the
מאפה תנור, ma'afeh tanur, וכי תקריב מנחה מאפה תנור סולת חלות מצות
בלולות בשמן, V'chi sakriv mincha ma'afeh tanur soles chalos matzos belulos bashemen,
so you bring חלות, chalos, ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן U'rekikei matzos meshuchim
bashemen and wafers. תקריב, Takriv, when you choose to bring, meaning
דבר רשות, devar reshus, this is totally optional, nobody's obligating you to
bring this מנחה. mincha. Okay, so you are choosing to bring
מאפה תנור ma'afeh tanur קרבן מנחה. korban mincha. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar
Rabbi Yehuda, מנין לאומר הרי עלי מנחת מאפה שלא יביא מחצה חלות
ומחצה רקיקין, minalayin l'omer harei alai minchas ma'afeh shelo yavi mechtzah chalos
u'mechtzah rekikin? don't bring half and half, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar קרבן
מנחה, korban mincha, so אמר קרבן מנחה amar korban mincha and
it can be either this or that. קרבן אחד אמרתי לך ולא
שנים ושלשה קרבנות. Korban echad amarti lecha v'lo shenayim u'sheloshah korbanos. It
has to be of one type, it can't be two or three
different types, so it can't be mixed. קרבן Korban means one. אמר
לו רבי שמעון, Amar lo Rabbi Shimon,
וכי נאמר קרבן קרבן שתי פעמים? v'chi neemar korban korban shtei peamim?
It doesn't say קרבן חלות מצות בלולות בשמן וקרבן, korban chalos matzos
belulos bashemen v'korban, you
know, רקיקי מצות, rekikei matzos, which would say this way is a
קרבן korban and that way is a separate קרבן. korban. It uses
the one word קרבן korban for the two types. So it says,
הרי לא נאמר אלא קרבן אחד. harei lo neemar ela korban echad.
It only says the word קרבן korban once. ונאמר בו, V'neemar bo,
and under the header of קרבן, korban, what does it say? חלות
ורקיקין. chalos u'rekikin. It gives you both the option of חלה chalah
and the option of רקיק, rekik, really very reasonable read of the
פסוק. pasuk. מעתה, me'atah, from this I'll infer, רצה להביא חלות ratzah
l'havi chalos so you want you can do all חלות chalos מביא,
mevi, רקיקין מביא, rekikin mevi, all the wafers maybe, מחצה חלות ומחצה
רקיקין מביא, mechtzah chalos u'mechtzah rekikin mevi, half and half, so you
can do. Now, the one question is, how do you do a
קמיצה kmitzah for half and half? How do you do a קמיצה
kmitzah from both genres? So here's how you do it. ובוללן, ubolelan,
you mix them up, this is actually after you sort of break
it into little pieces. After you bake it, you break it into
little pieces and then you mix them all up, וקומץ משניהם, v'komaitz
mishneihem, and you take your קמיצה kmitzah from a mixture of the
two of them, and therefore represents both מינים. minim. ואם קמץ ועלה
בידו מאחד על שניהם, V'im kamatz v'alah beyado m'echad al sheneihem, and
if you actually did a קמיצה kmitzah and you only got in
your hand the one of one of the types, יצא, yatza, you're
also יוצא, yotzei, which totally makes sense because Rabbi Shimon's whole position
is this is not fundamentally a different קרבן, korban, it's a variation
of how to bring this קרבן. korban. You do it this way
or that way, so at the end of the day, it's all
one קרבן korban and you can even bring from one of the
types for the other because it's all one. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda says, מנין
לאומר הרי עלי מנחת מאפה minalayin l'omer harei alai minchas ma'afeh שלא
יביא מחצה חלות ומחצה רקיקין? shelo yavi mechtzah chalos u'mechtzah rekikin, So
he's saying the same as Rabbi Yehuda, but he's going to quote
a different פסוק. pasuk. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, וכל מנחה אשר תאפה
בתנור, v'chol mincha asher te'afeh batanur, anything baked in an oven, וכל
נעשה במרחשת ועל מחבת, v'chol na'aseh bamarcheses v'al machavas, or the מרחשת
marcheses and the מחבת. machavas.
So those are the three primary sort of baked types of מנחות
minchos mentioned in the beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra, right? לכהן המקריב אותה
לו תהיה. l'kohen hamakriv osah lo sihiyeh. It goes to the כהן
Kohen who offers it up. And then it says, this is all
the פסוק pasuk in צו, Tzav, וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן וחרבה. v'chol
mincha belulah bashemen v'charevah. If it's not baked, there are two variations
of not baked. What are the two variations of not baked? בלולה
בשמן, belulah bashemen, mixed with oil but unbaked, that's the first one
mentioned in ויקרא, Vayikra, simply dough.
וחרבה, v'charevah, a desolate... barren, because that's the מנחת חוטא minchat chote
or סוטה sotah that has no oil. So by the way, that's
just פשט pshat in the פסוקים. psukim. The first three are the
baked types of מנחה: mincha: oven, frying pan, and the whatever deep
pan. And then בלולה בשמן וחרבה belula bashemen v'chareiva are the two
unbaked מנחה. mincha.
It's just plain flour. Flour, flour. Not baked, nothing. Just oil and
flour. Exactly.
That is exactly what it is. Right? That's the—that's the מנחת חוטא
minchat chote or מנחת סוטה. minchat sotah. And then the בלולה בשמן
belula bashemen is flour but not baked. So then it says, what
does the פסוק pasuk say about those? וכל בני אהרן תהיה. V'chol
bnei Aharon tihyeh.
Every—it's shared by בני אהרן. bnei Aharon. Now by the way, פשט
pshat of the פסוק pasuk does say, you know, this is basically
completely sort of—not ignored, but reconciled or smoothed over by חזל. chazal.
If you read closely the פסוקים psukim in ויקרא Vayikra and צו,
Tzav, it says certain things go to the כהן kohen who offers
it, and certain things are shared by all the כהנים. kohanim. חזל
chazal basically eliminate the כהן kohen who offers it and says every
קרבן korban that's brought, you know, gets shared by all of the
כהנים kohanim equally that are working that day. But anyway, פשט pshat
of the פסוקים psukim is saying it matters. The baked type go
to, you know, the כהן kohen that brings it, and the—and the
non-baked types are shared equally. Anyway, be that as it may, what
he's going to דרש drash is the following. At the end of
the פסוק, pasuk, the two not baked types are radically different, right?
They're totally different קרבנות. korbanot. One is a חוטא, chote, one is
a נדבה. nedava. Anyway, they're radically different. In the first part, also
מרחשת marcheshet and מחבת machabat are completely different קרבנות. korbanot. So since
the first part has two things that are completely different, the last
part has two קרבנות korbanot which are completely different, when it mentions
מאפה תנור, ma'afeh tanur, so that is referred to—that is—it—what we can
learn from that is it has within it two types of קרבנות
korbanot which are completely different. Again, that's a simple—that, you know, a
reasonable thing to learn into, but that's what he says. So let's
take a look. מה—okay, Ma תהיה. tihyeh. מה וכל האמור למטה שני
מינין חלוקין אף וכל האמור למעלה שני מינין חלוקין. Ma v'chol ha'amor
lemata shnei minin chalukin, af v'chol ha'amor lemala shnei minin chalukin. So
the same way what's said below by the—by the—two unbaked types, they're
two completely different types, אף וכל האמור למעלה שני מינין חלוקין. af
v'chol ha'amor lemala shnei minin chalukin.
So therefore the וכל, v'chol, when it says וכל מנחה, v'chol mincha,
וכל, v'chol, when it says וכל v'chol at the bottom it refers
to two totally separate types, when it says וכל v'chol at the
top, two totally separate types. So the מאפה תנור, ma'afeh tanur, the
two variations would be completely separate and you cannot bring half and
half. Okay, so that's the debate. So now the גמרא gemara says,
רבי יהודה שפיר קאמר רבי שמעון. Rabbi Yehuda shapir qamar Rabbi Shimon.
So now Rabbi Yehuda, how do you respond to Rabbi Shimon? He
gives a very good read of the פסוק. pasuk. It says one
word קרבן korban and then it says two ways of bringing it.
So presumably those are all one type of a קרבן, korban, not
two types of a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא gemara says, no.
אמר לך היא תיובתא היא כיון דכתיב בשמן בשמן כמאן דכתיב קרבן
קרבן דמי. Amar lach hi teivuta hi, keivan d'khtiv bashemen bashemen k'man
d'khtiv korban korban dami. No, because what does—again, what does the פסוק
pasuk say? וכי תקריב קרבן מנחה מאפה תנור סלת חלות מצות בלולת
בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן. V'khi takriv korban mincha ma'afeh tanur, solet
chalot matzot blulot bashemen, urkikei matzot mshuchim bashemen. So since it mentions
שמן shemen twice, that's basically telling you these are two completely separate
options, you cannot merge them, they are distinct. So that what to
me makes them distinct options. So what would Rabbi Shimon say back?
ורבי שמעון היא רבי שמעון V'Rabbi Shimon, hi Rabbi Shimon would say
back, אי לאו דכתיב בשמן בשמן, ee lo khtiv bashemen bashemen, if
it did not say בשמן bashemen twice to distinguish the two, הוה
אמינא דוקא מחצה חלות ומחצה רקיקין. hava amina davka mechtza chalot mechtza
rekikin. Your only option is half and half, which some could actually
say maybe actually is פשט pshat in the פסוק. pasuk. מאפה תנור
ma'afeh tanur you bring of two types. So Rabbi Shimon says I
might have thought that. So אבל חלות לחודייהו ורקיקין לחודייהו אימא לא.
aval chalot l'chudai v'rekikin l'chudai eima lo.
I might have thought that you don't have the option of bringing
all of one type, all of the other type. קא משמע לן
Kamashma lan not that way, that you can bring all of one.
So Rabbi Shimon has a very nice read of the פסוק. pasuk.
He says the פסוקים psukim do to some degree distinguish them, it
says בשמן bashemen twice, it's a little redundant, so it tells you
you could bring one—all of one or all of the other, but
because it puts it all under the header of קרבן, korban, it's
also to tell you that you can bring of both genres, five
loaves of each and mix it. Again, notice by the way the
assumption that a מנחה mincha would be brought out of ten loaves,
that's not even stated, but it's, you know, what—actually here it didn't
state, it just said מחצה מחצה. mechtza mechtza. But anyway, in other
places it says five and five. Okay, so that's Rabbi Shimon, you
have the option of merging it. Now the גמרא gemara says רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה היינו אבוה. Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda hainu avuha. Rabbi
Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda is sort of the same as his father. The
father said all one, all the other, Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda said
the same thing, he just quoted a different פסוק. pasuk. So the
גמרא gemara could say maybe he is saying the same thing, he's
just quoting a different פסוק. pasuk. But it says no, איכא בינייהו
דיעבד. ika beinaihu d'avad. Notice again the d-i-a-v-a-d, it's d-i-a-v-a-d not d-e-v-e-d
as one word, d-i-a-v-a-d if you actually did it. בדיעבד. b'diavad. If
you actually chose to do half and half are you יוצא? yotze?
So the גמרא gemara says that he really emphasizes that you're not.
The same way you would not be יוצא yotze if I said
I'm going to bring a מנחת מחבת minchat machabat and I brought
part of it as מרחשת marcheshet because it's completely different, so here
too because he's putting it in the context of things that are
completely different, for him if you brought, you know, a mixture, you
would completely—you would not be יוצא yotze even בדיעבד. b'diavad. It's a
completely different קרבן. korban. But according to the father, he's not saying
it's completely different, he's just saying that you're supposed to bring of
one type, but if you actually did bring of the other type,
that would still be under the header of מאפה תנור ma'afeh tanur
and you would be יוצא. yotze. הדרן עלך כל המנחות. Hadran alach
kol haminchot. So that is the end of that פרק, perek, a
פרק perek which is really very focused on getting us to the
techni—the practical reality of what a מנחה mincha is. And now we're
going to start רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael which is again very appropriate
to the time of year we are on. This entire פרק Perek
is devoted to the bringing of the עומר, Omer, okay, and actually
it's going to get into the מצווה Mitzvah of ספירת העומר. Sefiras
HaOmer. So anyway. So let's take a look now with the beginning
of רבי ישמעאל. Rabi Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל אומר. Rabi Yishmael Omer. רבי
ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael says אומר, Omer, actually some have it העומר, HaOmer,
which is more grammatically correct and also easier to say than רבי
ישמעאל אומר אומר. Rabi Yishmael Omer Omer. Okay, רבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabi
Yishmael Omer, so Rabbi Ishmael says העומר היה בא בשבת משלוש סאים,
HaOmer Hayah Ba BeShabbos MeShalosh Se'im, if you would bring it on
שבת, Shabbos, if the sixteenth of ניסן Nissan would fall out on
שבת, Shabbos, what would you do? משלוש סאים, MeShalosh Se'im, you would
use three סאים Se'im of grain from which to process your עישרון,
Issaron, your you know your small amount of flour. What exactly is
the proportion? I am forgetting. Is there a Frank dictionary or has
he got some of those good? No, over there on the shelf
Shas right there.
So let's take a look.
סאה Se'ah is I'll tell you how
many. סאה Se'ah is what's the proportion of a סאה Se'ah to
an עישרון? Issaron?
Okay, there are three and a third עשרונות Esronos to a סאה.
Se'ah. So three סאים Se'im is oh that makes sense. No it
doesn't really because עישרון Issaron is a tenth of not a tenth
of three but anyway.
Okay anyway. Okay so if you start with three סאים Se'im and
you get an עישרון Issaron then you're getting one tenth of the
volume from all of this wheat after you process it and sift
it and you get the fine flour it's going to be one
tenth of what you started from. That's if you start with three
סאים. Se'im. So he says if it's coming on שבת Shabbos you
start with three סאים Se'im to get your עישרון. Issaron. ובחול מחמש,
UveChol MeChamesh,
but on a weekday you use even more grain and you get
your עישרון Issaron out of חמש סאין. Chamesh Se'in. וחכמים אומרים, VeChachamim
Omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say there's no difference שבת Shabbos and weekday.
אחד בשבת ואחד בחול משלוש היה בא. Echad BeShabbos VeEchad BeChol MeShalosh
Hayah Ba. No difference but actually it was a lesser amount it
was three. Obviously רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael is trying to minimize the
amount of מלאכה Melacha you do on שבת, Shabbos, so he wants
you to start with you have to cut because we're going to
find out you actually cut it on שבת Shabbos as well if
the sixteenth fell out on שבת. Shabbos. So anyway so you he
wants you to be cutting less grain, threshing less grain, grinding less
grain, he wants you to be doing with less. The חכמים Chachamim
don't feel it has to be less. On the other hand they're
adopting the minimum amount, three סאים, Se'im, so they never assume any
more. Okay. משלוש היה בא. MeShalosh Hayah Ba. רבי חנניה סגן הכהנים
אומר, Rabi Chananya Segan HaKohanim Omer, Rabbi Chananya the assistant כהן Kohen
of Kohanim says, בשבת היה נקצר ביחיד ובמגל אחד ובקופה אחת. BeShabbos
Hayah Niktzar BeYachid UveMagal Echad UveKupah Achas. On שבת Shabbos they would
do it without a big commotion, they would do it with an
individual כהן Kohen would be sent out a person would be sent
out to do it and he'd use one scythe and one קופה,
Kupah, one like basket to collect the wheat. ובחול, UveChol, and on
a weekday בשלושה ובשלוש קופות ובשלושה מגלות. BeShlosha UveShalosh Kupos UveShlosha Magalos.
You'd send out three people and three
baskets and three scythes. וחכמים אומרים, VeChachamim Omrim, אחד שבת ואחד חול
בשלושה ובשלוש קופות ובשלושה מגלות. Echad Shabbos VeEchad Chol BeShlosha UveShalosh Kupos
UveShlosha Magalos.
Three people, three scythes, three baskets. So what is the issue here?
Part of the issue that we're going to find in the גמרא
Gemara is it's sort of להוציא מלבן של צדוקין. Lehotzi MiLiban Shel
Tzadukim. That they had the whole issue about you know as you
know a whole debate about when שבועות Shavuos fell out, so they
wanted and and would it be דוחה שבת, Docheh Shabbos, especially if
you don't if you don't agree that this is actually when you
when you bring the עומר, Omer, not what's when it should fall
out but when you start with the עומר. Omer. So they made
a big deal of yes we're going to do it very publicly
on שבת Shabbos whereas the other person either might have felt that
you know why would you try to do it more privately or
smaller. A maybe to minimize the amount of חילול שבת Chilul Shabbos
is a possibility. But also you know because of like bringing a
violation of שבת Shabbos outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. It's
a fascinating phenomenon the עומר. Omer. Normally you override שבת Shabbos in
the מקדש, Mikdash, you bring the קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur in the
מקדש, Mikdash, but you don't actually violate it out of the מקדש
Mikdash right for the sake of the מקדש, Mikdash, but for the
עומר Omer the cutting of the עומר Omer you did. So how
much are we really going to bring that experience out of the
מקדש? Mikdash? That's an important question. Okay.
Wouldn't חנניה סגן הכהנים Chananya Segan HaKohanim have known? Right.
He actually had to look
at the I have to look up the eyewitness.
Right. Presumably yeah he would know. That is a very good point.
I have to I have to look up the exact dating. I
know the סגן הכהנים Segan HaKohanim title is suggestive. Okay I'll try
to look up the dating his dating. Okay let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. בשלמא רבנן, Bishlama Rabbanan, I understand the Rabbis,
קסברי עישרון מובחר משלוש סאין, Kasavri Issaron Muvchar MiShalosh Se'in, or משלוש
סאין, MeShalosh Se'in,
you can get a good עישרון Issaron a fine flour out of
three סאין, Se'in, a one to ten ratio. אתי בשלוש בחול ובשלוש
בשבת, Ati BeShalosh BeChol UveShalosh BeShabbos, so they're not going to change
it whether the weekday or שבת. Shabbos. אלא רבי ישמעאל, Ela Rabi
Yishmael, when it comes to Rabbi Ishmael, מאי קסבר? Mai Kasavar? What
is he of the opinion of?
אי קסבר עישרון מובחר לא אתי אלא מחמש, Ei Kasavar Issaron Muvchar
Lo Ati Ela MeChamesh, if he holds that a choice עישרון Issaron
you need to start from five... with five סאין, se'in, אפילו בשבת
נמי, afilu b'Shabbos nami, so okay, the עומר Omer overrides שבת, Shabbos,
do it even on שבת. Shabbos. אי משלש אתי, Ei mishalosh ati,
if it can come from three סאה se'ah you can get a
choice עשרון, issaron, so אתי אפילו בחול נמי, ati afilu b'chol nami,
so why do five on the weekday, do three? So אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says, קסבר רבי ישמעאל עשרון מובחר בלא
טרחה אתי מחמש, בטרחה אתי משלש. kasavar Rabbi Ishmael issaron muvchar belo
tircha ati mechamesh, b'tircha ati mishalosh. Yes,
it's easier to get it from five. Why? Because again, what are
you trying to do? You're trying to get the finest flour. So
if you start with a lot, right, what do you use? You
use a sieve that has small holes, so only like after you
grind it, only the fine flour comes out. So if you start
with a greater quantity, you don't have to do as much sifting.
You don't have to do as much of this stuff. It comes
out easier, the first sort of amount comes out without as much
effort. So if you start with a larger quantity, yes, if you
start with three סאה se'ah you can get an עשרון issaron of
fine flour, but you have to work more, you have to do
more of the sifting.
Yeah, wait a second, why do we sift at all on שבת?
Shabbos?
That's coming up in a later משנה. mishnah. Now we're just working
with that assumption, okay? But we will see that in a later
משנה. mishnah. Right, why not cut it before שבת Shabbos and bring
it on שבת? Shabbos? Right, even if the קרבן korban is on
שבת, Shabbos, right, why don't you just sift it and get the
whole thing ready before שבת? Shabbos? So we'll see about that later.
Okay, I know, but the question is why not cut it a
day before, two days before and get it ready? That could be,
but we'll see anyway, we'll see it later on. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says so therefore it's more טרחה tircha to get it
out of three. So therefore what do we say? בחול, B'chol, on
a weekday, מייתינן מחמש, maityinan mechamesh, דהא שכיחא מילתא. de-ha shechicha milta.
On חול chol you, on a weekday, you get it out of
five, that's more sort of praiseworthy, first of all it makes it
easier for us, second of all it's, you know, it makes it
sound choicer, oh you know we had to get five סאין se'in
to get this one עשרון. issaron. Okay, anyway, so that's more appropriate.
בשבת, B'Shabbos, but on שבת, Shabbos, מוטב שירבה במלאכה אחת בהרקדה, mutav
she-yarbeh b'melacha achas b'harkada, better to make more effort doing one מלאכה
melacha over and over again, right, the sort of sifting, ואל ירבה
במלאכות הרבה, v'al yarbeh b'melachos harbeh, don't do a lot of different
מלאכות. melachos. What would you have to do? You'd have to do
less sifting if you started with five סאה, se'ah, but what would
you have to do? You'd have to get two more סאין. se'in.
Think about the amount of מלאכות melachos that are involved in it.
If you look at רש"י, Rashi, the second wide line near the
end, ואל ירבה במלאכות הרבה, v'al yarbeh b'melachos harbeh, רש"י Rashi tells
you how what you have to, how many מלאכות melachos you have
to do in order to get flour: שיקצור she-yiktzor you cut, ויזרה
v'yizreh you winnow, ויברור v'yivror you do בורר, borer, ויטחן v'yitchan and
you grind, וירקד v'yirkod and then you sift. So that's a lot
of מלאכות melachos to get those two extra סאין se'in rather than
start with fewer סאה se'ah and do more מרקד. meraked. Now it's
an interesting question about
who
really cares? Meaning at the end of the day, like if I
did מרקד meraked ten times or I did ten separate מלאכות, melachos,
haven't I violated שבת Shabbos ten times one way or the other?
Why is one better or worse? So you could say that it's
not really so much, you know, הלכתית halachically worse, but it's more
like in terms of what it does to the experience of שבת.
Shabbos. You know, the experience of שבת Shabbos is violated more if
you're doing different types of מלאכות melachos at an experiential level, you
know, than if you're just, okay, you're violating one thing but you
keep on doing it again and again and again, you know, you're
not violating in different ways, experientially it's less, you know, it's less
sort of a rupture of שבת. Shabbos. The interesting question to ask
is, is that just experientially or does that also have like הלכתי
halachic significance? You know, do we say that somehow there is more
of a חילול שבת chilul Shabbos when different ranges of מלאכות melachos
are done, not just experientially it more affects the fabric of שבת.
Shabbos.
Yeah, we certainly have it in terms of the
חובה קרבן,
chovah korban, you
know if
it's בשוגג...
b'shogeg...
Right, but for one מלאכה melacha you would bring
one, but if there's העלם ידיעה בינתים. he-elam yediyah beintayim. But right,
if there's one שכחת שבת shikchas Shabbos let's say, then and you
only do one מלאכה melacha multiple times, so in that way you're
right, it does sort of focus the sense of, it could be
understood there as correct, he's also sort of limiting the sense of
violation.
Right, if a doctor is allowed to go into the hospital on
שבת, Shabbos, right, but once they're there they have to limit, they
can't just... Right, well that's their... violating שבת... Shabbos...
Right, it's not like a blanket allowance, right, and that's another point
as well to be recognized that even when you have these allowances,
to some degree it's sometimes it's הותרה hutra versus דחויה, dechuyah, but
nevertheless even when you have these allowances, how do you do it
in a way that minimizes the impact on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so
let's just read one more line here. Okay,
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says, רבי ישמעאל ורבי שמעון
בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה, Rabbi Ishmael v'Rabbi Shimon beno shel
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, two different people, אמרו דבר אחד, amru davar
echad, they said essentially the same thing. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael is
trying to minimize the חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos, or חילול chilul is
the wrong word, but anyway the incursion into שבת, Shabbos, and that's
similar to רבי שמעון בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה. Rabbi Shimon
beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. Where do you know that? דתניא,
De-tanya, we learn in a ברייתא, braita, ארבעה עשר שחל להיות בשבת,
arba-asar she-chal lihyos b'Shabbos, here's another great example when you have to
override שבת. Shabbos. The fourteenth of ניסן Nisan occurs on שבת, Shabbos,
so you're going to bring the קרבן פסח korban Pesach anyway, מפשיט
את הפסח עד החזה, mapshit es ha-Pesach ad ha-chazeh,
you skin the פסח Pesach until the breast... פסח Pesach till the
chest. You skin from the feet down or if feet up, but
I mean they hung it by its feet. So you skin starting
at the feet. So you skin it off until you get to
the chest which exposes the whole like the whole belly and therefore
that allows you to cut it open and to take out the
אימורים. eimurim. So that's what you'd have to do because you bring,
you burn the אימורים eimurim even though it's שבת. Shabbos. If you're
allowed to bring the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, you would not only
זורק zorek the דם dam but you bring the אימורים. eimurim. But
you would not totally flay it, you would not totally remove the
skin.
That's דברי divrei רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi
Yishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka trying to limit the amount
of flaying that you're doing on שבת, Shabbos, so it's not necessary
to flay the whole thing, so don't flay the whole thing. וחכמים
אומרים Vachachamim omrim and the חכמים Chachamim say עד שיפשיט כולו, ad
sheyafshis kulo, no, you flay it all. So you see, שבת Shabbos
you're allowed to do it and רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka is still
trying to limit the amount of, sort of incursion that is happening.
So you see they're saying essentially the same thing. מי לא אמר
רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא התם Mi lo amar
Rabbi Yishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hasam what?
Do we see that by the standard שבת Shabbos קרבנות? korbanos?
No. But this is, oh, you mean why does he just say
it by קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? Why doesn't he say it by
other קרבנות korbanos like by the תמיד tamid that you don't do,
well the תמיד tamid is an עולה olah so it's all burnt
and the normal מוספין musafin are עולות. olos. The question would be
like the שעיר לחטאת se'ir l'chatas that you bring on a רגל.
regel. What would he say there?
That's interesting. I don't know. Okay, so anyway, so גמרא Gemara says
like this, מי לא אמר רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא התם כל היכא דאפשר לא טרחינן mi lo amar Rabbi Yishmael
bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hasam kol heicha de'efshar lo tarchinan
that as much as possible we don't do extra effort on שבת.
Shabbos. Is that just effort? But you know, more violation than is
necessary. הכא נמי, Hacha nami, so here too by the עומר, omer,
כיון דאפשר לא טרחינן keivan de'efshar lo tarchinan we don't do more
than is necessary, we don't do five סאים. se'im. So גמרא Gemara
says, so you see essentially it's the same approach. גמרא Gemara says,
all right, it's similar but it's not identical. ממאי, Mimai, how do
you know it's really the same?
דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי ישמעאל התם Dilma ad kan lo
ka'amar Rabbi Yishmael hasam maybe רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says limit it
by the עומר? omer? No, אלא משום בזיון קדשים. ela mishum bizayon
kodshim. You're not leaving a קרבן korban looking disfigured, you know somehow
mistreated. But to half-flay an animal does not seem respectful to what
you do with a
קרבן. korban. אבל התם איכא בזיון קדשים Aval hasam ika bizayon kodshim
there where the קרבן korban is somehow being, you know degraded, אימא
כרבנן פליגי eima k'rabbanan peligi maybe he'll say in that case, I
would actually flay it completely. I'm only willing to do it if
all it's about is more or less effort, but not if there's
some other consequence. In that type of a case I'd say flay
it completely. אי נמי I nami or the reverse, עד כאן לא
קאמר רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא התם ad kan
lo ka'amar Rabbi Yishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hasam when
does רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael bno
shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka say flay it halfway? אלא דאיתעביד ליה
לצורך גבוה Ela de'is'avid lei l'tzorech gavoah ולא לצורך חולי שבת. v'lo
l'tzorech chulei Shabbos. That you've done everything you needed to do for
God. You've gotten to the point where you can get out the
אימורים. eimurim. And any more flaying is not warranted because it's no
longer serving God's needs, as it were, religious needs. אבל הכא דלא
איתעביד ליה לצורך גבוה, Aval hacha d'lo is'avid lei l'tzorech gavoah, first
of all you're not done, you when you're, you have yet
to have done the sifting, you're still cutting the grain, וצריך לחולי
שבת v'tzarich l'chulei Shabbos and you need to violate שבת. Shabbos. So
therefore you're at an earlier stage, אימא כרבנן פליגי eima k'rabbanan peligi
maybe he'll hold like the Rabbis. Meaning what's the difference? There as
soon as you get to the chest, you say well why do
I need to progress? I've gotten as far as I need to
go. Okay, whereas there you could say, you know, yes I cut
it three, but is it as far as I need to go?
Maybe not because I keep on cutting more, it'll make the processing
easier. So it's not like the extra two are not needed. They
are needed if you want to make a finer grain or you
want to make it easier, so therefore maybe it would be more
warranted in that case. So the point is, yes there's generally the
same opinion, we try to limit the amount of violation of שבת
Shabbos even when it's allowed, but there's nuance, possible nuance differences because
exactly the, you know, the calculus of what is it warranted and
when is it not warranted could differ from case to case.